this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC Radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software digitalocean is the easiest
cloud platform to deploy manage and
scale applications of any size
removing infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/ SC radio for software engineering
radio amela in the Salinas today I have
with me Pat Helland Pat is a principal
software architect at Salesforce working
on a cloud-based multi-tenant database
technology Pat has been working on
databases transactions and distributed
systems since 1978 previously he worked
on the big data plumbing for Bing at
Microsoft Pat co-authored the article
titled too big not to fail and brace
failure so it doesn't embrace you
paddles or writes a column for the ACM
Pat welcome to the show thank you thank
you for having me today we're gonna be
talking about web scale failure and
recovery
I read your ACM column title too big not
to fail embrace failure so it doesn't
embrace you you begin talking about web
scale computing and how this means
running hundreds of thousands of servers
can you give a bit more detail about
what web scale computing is well thank
you for having me there's a lot of
things that are happening with the web
as we all know right you have Google you
have Amazon you've Salesforce you have
all of these companies doing work in the
demand that any of these websites sees
gets larger and smaller over time
I mean tip
throughout the day throughout the
seasons shopping season can make a big
difference and so you have to provision
your data centers to be able to accept a
lot lot lot of traffic and to be able to
manage when it gets larger and smaller
and so you usually end up in a world
where there are tens and hundreds of
thousands of servers that are all
working together to provide a function
and just the management of them the life
cycle of what happens to a server is in
an in and of its own right a fascinating
area
you mentioned servers that you can be
running tens of thousands of servers
sometimes hundreds of those hundreds of
thousands so scale computing involves
physical hardware and also software for
example servers like you just mentioned
and we also have VMs and containers can
you explain these three components we
can start with servers sure a server is
a physical box you can walk into a data
center in kick a server it's there you
can touch it it takes electricity a VM
is a virtual machine and that allows the
software to pretend that the VM is its
own server but what's really interesting
and cool about VM technology is you can
run lots of things that look like
physical servers on the same honest to
gosh server sharing those resources and
using it to protect from one another as
they use the same resources now within
that environment you have components
components are a really interesting
technology that's emerged over the last
10 15 years which allows the easy
deployment of software in the easy
they're lighter weight and they run
inside of VMs or maybe in a physical
machine but usually inside of a VM and
they typically run as micro services
where you can have a lot of computers
running the same software doing the same
job in a fashion that adapts as the load
comes and goes and adapts as things
break the last one you're referring to
are the containers right the containers
yes
and they also make it easy with the
micro service approach to containers to
allowing you to roll out new software
so pool you might have a few hundred of
these running a particular job on your
website and then you can evolve the
software you always have to upgrade and
change the software and you might end up
out of two hundred servers on one
hundred and fifty or running the old
stuff and fifty are running the new
stuff as you're making changes I was
reading about your career and I saw that
you've spent the majority of your almost
40-year career working on transactions
also distributed systems and a signal of
all we know have transactional
environments that can operate at a large
scale in your other ACM call Youm titled
life beyond distributed transactions you
talk about this thought experiment about
almost infinite scaling can you explain
what this thought experiment is about
well it's not easy there's some people
who argue it's possible but it's not
easy to actually make transactions run
across a very very large set of servers
and and certainly across trusts
environments where you don't know that
the other computation involved over
there is part of the same department or
company but if you're trying to run and
make a bunch of changes it's it's hard
to make sure that they keep going when
something fails a transaction is can I
do the same thing and have work split
into pieces across multiple servers and
have all of it happen or none of it
happen
so that the programmer doesn't have to
think about partial results I'm changing
this I'm changing that but I don't have
to worry about this happening without
that happening in many ways though as
you spread this across servers it
becomes very similar to getting married
on the telephone people ask about
atomicity in a transaction did it all
happen or none of it happen and to me
that's like is the husband married but
the wife is not married or it turns out
the way we think of marriage both of
them are married or neither of them are
married and that's an atomic commitment
to make it all happen together but what
if you're getting married on the
telephone what if you're on the phone
and you know the person you want to
marry is in another country
they ask will you take this person to be
your wife her husband and you say I do
and then you get a dial tone
yeah there's a real dilemma here are you
allowed to go on a date tonight can you
do that and the answer is that atomic
transaction depends upon being able to
communicate and so there's some good
theory that's come out that's been
proven you know that you can't really
know how to do that when there's
failures in between and keep
availability and that's called the cap
conjecture consistency availability and
partition tolerance and you have all
three and it's been proven that if it's
a classic notion of consistency where
I'm making changes in you're making
changes if you can't quite happen so
easily mm-hmm that make sense yes that
makes sense you mentioned a couple of
things
consistency availability and partition
tolerance yes I guess the one you're
referring to win in this phone call
example is consistency right and also
availability well in partition tolerance
when I got the dial tone I got a
partition okay I I can't communicate
across the telephone when I got the dial
tone and so now I need to find out how
can this person I want to get married
and I both have the same outcome we're
married or were not married but there's
a dial tone in the middle and so the
answer is you know the typical answer is
you wait you wait until you reconnect
and you find out hey what'd you say did
you say I do I said I do are we married
and that would be where the availability
suffers because of the dial tone until
you can figure out how to get that
answer that's consistent if you want to
go do your own thing without waiting for
the reconnection of the telephone call
then you want to have availability and
continue to move ahead but you don't
know the outcome yet so you're giving up
the consistency the classic consistency
of I want to make a change in you want
to make a change and we both agree on
that change this example that you just
explained illustrates a failure
happening when we're talking about
web-scale and operating with servers
things can break and servers can fail
they always break they
all these break what are some of the
reasons why a server in a data center
can fail
well they first of all servers are
incredibly reliable there's just a lot
of them and so some of them are broken
disk drives are spinning things and they
fail you know they they fail at a rate
of you know one will fail every four or
five years kind of a thing I mean you
you look at the statistics and they will
break out of nowhere power supplies can
go out lots of things can happen so that
the physical box that you purchased from
the vendor no longer is functioning and
you have to realize the way I think
about servers in a data center is like a
bag of nails on a construction site
they're all the same once in a while
ones bent and you throw it aside and you
pick it up and you try to use them and
no one walks into a construction site
loving and caring for each individual
nail you try to make sure you have
enough nails by weight that you have
extras see so you can cope with things
going wrong and some nails that get
thrown away these don't have a specific
personality now when you try to think
about that as a complex computer that's
participating in the cluster of the data
center you have to think about how am I
gonna be okay if this one breaks how am
I going to continue to provide the web
service that my website has signed up to
do when a server will just plain break
that I mean if you have you know a bunch
of servers and you go and like tens of
thousands of servers and you go home for
the weekend pretty much what you do on
Monday morning is figure out which ones
to unplug into and to send off and plug
new ones back in because there's gonna
be some broken in the morning that's a
good analogy because in the construction
if if you're gonna broke a nail the
whole construction is not shutdown right
things keep going and that would yeah
very similar to what we should react in
the sense I'm sure one server went down
and right you bring extra nails you
don't get emotional about it you don't
hold a funeral for the nail you just
move on what is an example of this of
the signing to expect failure without
having human intervention and making
sure things keep going well for
example you know the distributed systems
things that hold data HDFS is a great
example right every piece of data is in
a block and every block has put on three
different servers and part of this
system is constantly watching can I
still talk to all of the servers that
have got my data I may have 20,000
servers that are part of an HDFS cluster
and the name note is talking to them and
making sure they're alive if one of them
is not alive then it's got a list of
where the copies of data are kept right
oh that this particular block is on
these three servers including the one
that failed that other particular block
is on those other three servers
including the one that failed and if one
fails the misses oh my gosh I got some
work to do and starts telling each of
the servers that had a block that you
know was also on the server that failed
go put that block back to be in a third
place so if you think about it if a
server has I don't know maybe a hundred
thousand blocks on it and it fails the
second and third copies of those hundred
thousand blocks are kept on different
servers spread around the data center
and if you've dropped those server
replicas from three to two wow you got a
problem you don't of crisis but you have
a problem and so the problem gets solved
by finding a place to put a third copy
for each and every one of them and you
want to spread it around if you do this
well and HDFS does then the act of going
from where you've dropped down to two
copies up to three takes less time than
it would to actually copy all of the
data out of the one server that died the
reason is because the second and third
copies are in so many different servers
who are going to talk to so many other
different servers that in parallel you
can get back to coping with the loss of
a server in much less time than it would
take to actually read and write a single
server by getting back up to three
replicas of that data Wow
you are now back to the point where you
can take a look in and continue on my
joking way of thinking about this is it
would be great to be able to walk into a
data center with a baseball bat and
whack a rack of
servers which drops the replicas for a
bunch of data down to two and now the
system says oh and makes three replicas
spread out across lots of different
racks and by the time you raise the
baseball bat to hit another rack
everything was back to three so it can
take another hit now that's of course an
exaggeration but it's how to think about
it the failure is quickly repaired the
faster it's repaired the more available
the underlying data is and that's the
way we have to think about things in the
data center so I see at least two design
principles here one is first of all have
your data replicated have more than one
copy of it available and also learn to
recover quickly
if correct Yale ability is a function of
how often failures occur which is called
mean time between failure and how
quickly you can recover from the failure
mean time to repair and so if you can
recover quickly then your overall
availability of the data goes way up
there's a there's another point when
dealing with data which is that it's
actually a lot easier to do these
algorithms if the underlying data that
you're keeping is not changing data
yes data you wrote once and you're gonna
read it a bunch of times maybe over
years and then you'll eventually maybe
throw it away but you're not gonna
actually change that data you'll write
other data rather than changing that
data and that's because that what that
means is as we go through this oh gee I
lost a replica I'm gonna go make some
more as you're going through that you
don't have to worry about the data being
changed that's a huge benefit one
example I can think of is somebody is
looking up a book or a section in a book
that that book has already been written
I know there are revisions that can make
a change but yes it's not the same as a
bank account number well let's talk
about those for just a second the
revision of the book okay is actually a
different book in this approach okay so
so you have the book for you know
revision one and then you have the book
revision two and maybe there's something
that says yeah if you want revision one
go look at this unique ID to go get the
data if you have revision to go look at
that unique ID to get the data but once
you get to the revision
it's a unique thing the other thing I
wanted to say you mentioned bank
accounts bank accounts it turns out are
handled as immutable data if you have
your may bank statement and you're
looking at your may bank statement to
understand the status of what's gone on
in the last year you have to look
through May and April in March in
February and January and look back
through them to interpret today
furthermore if you look at your May bank
statement and you say oh my gosh there's
a problem you call up the bank and you
say there's a problem and they say oh
yeah you're correct there's a problem
they don't issue a new May bank
statement they issue a change in the
June bank statement that has not yet
been sent to you and so from the
perspective of the bank there's just a
constant writing of stuff that once it
is written is never going to be changed
and change happens in the new things
that are yet to be written and then they
show up on your lab and so that makes
all of this mechanism work much easier
in a distributed system and that's why I
wrote the paper called immutability
changes everything is to get people's
awareness raised about this the
advantages and the phenomena of how
we're evolving to more and more data
being treated as immutable data I want
to talk about the hardware in the data
centers a little bit more sure again in
that column that you wrote too big not
to fail you talked about having to
change Hardware every three years I
think and also the cost of this so what
I want to ask you is why is it not cost
effective to keep the hardware for too
long in a data center well the hardware
itself gets a you know the new hardware
is more efficient than the old hardware
if you had a car from the 1960s and it
was getting 10 miles to the gallon you
know and the gasoline was most of what
you are spending to afford the usage of
the car most of it right that sometimes
is true sometimes it's not then you
might want to go down and get yourself a
new car that gets you know 40 miles to
the gallon because they're pretty good
at it nowadays or 35 miles to the gallon
and that in ends up lowering your cost
of ownership if the gasoline is a major
portion of the expense in data centers
today electricity and
the physical mission you know the
physical building the more electricity
are a much larger component over the
lifetime of a server than the cost of a
server so if you can only fit so many
racks of servers into your building and
you can only wire up so much electricity
and it's it's much more the electricity
than the physical space and you can go
get a computer now that gives you twice
as much computation for the same
electricity when is it a good idea to
spend some money to get that computer
that gives you more computation now
there's no perfect answer here but a
ballpark that we can all kind of keep in
mind is that the server is going to use
you're gonna replace it about every
three years now some of the costs of
replacing are decommissioning and then
commissioning the new server to
decommission it you have to get all the
traffic off you have to get all the data
you want off you have to unplug it you
frequently in many cases you want to
take the physical disks and the physical
SSDs and put them through a giant
shredder because you're very worried
about the data being snooped on and so
if you actually turn it into a bunch of
powdered iron dust by shredding it then
it's not so likely people are gonna
snoop on that data and so that's a huge
step that has to happen too now when you
Commission the Machine you have to bring
it in you have to verify it you have to
make sure it's looking pretty good you
have to install the software you have to
install the data then you can start
sending traffic to it each of those
things takes some time so one of the
concerns is if I've only got three years
between buying a piece a server and
using and throwing it away how long does
it take me to set it up and Commission
it and how long do I actually have to
spend decommissioning it and those are
will consume part of your 3-year window
that happens there so all of this
process is just a part of their routine
of of going through hardware in a data
center I'm very fond of saying that
electronics and roast-beef are worth
less next year and so it's kind of true
you buy that TV you know oh heck I was
over at a friend's neighbors across the
street and it
beautiful plasma TV he's got it over the
fireplace and we were joking about the
fact that if the TV gets messed up by
the fireplace it's probably not a big
deal because the plasma well it cost a
lot a few years ago there's something
down at the store that you can buy that
is gonna do a better job for not much
money and so the same thing happens with
servers in the data center do you know
the reason behind the 3-year window
that's a ballpark that's just the
mathematics of when you see an expected
reduction you know
the increase from Moore's Law and the
increase of what you're getting out of
the server it's been a rule of thumb
which gets revisited every time as to
how much more am I getting with the new
server versus how much does it cost me
to actually get rid of it and replace it
and put it in the figuring out when's
the value of the new server such that
it's worth taking out there's no there's
no magic about three years but it's kind
of held that way for sort of 10 years
just that the new ones with Moore's Law
are gonna give you enough to make it
better to replace them you also get
what's called a bathtub curve a bathtub
failure curve imagine I'm making a plot
over time where the x axis is time and
the y axis is failures how many
components out of 10,000 how many
servers at a 10,000 fail over you know
as time goes on and so initially when
you plug in a brand new server at first
some stuff fails in some percentage of
them don't do so well then you use them
for months and then it drops down and
they're very very reliable and not much
breaks and then as you start getting
past three four years into five years
then the failure rate starts going up
and the shape of this curve looks a lot
like a bathtub and that's why it's known
as a bathtub curve of failures over time
and so you kind of want to test your way
out of the initial failures that are
happening and you want to just retire
the server's before they start getting
really flaky later on in their lifetime
so you mentioned this bathtub curve and
I just want to recap to make sure I
understand is the bathtub corby
cuz you commissioned a new server and at
the beginning you see a lot of failures
so the number of failures is high but
then the server gets better and the
failures are dropping is that a lot well
then at some point those failures are
gonna rise again correct yes in and this
is normal in many many kinds of things
from cars to televisions to toasters and
that's why you see the 30-day warranty
on a lot of things is because you take
it home you try to use it it works and
then all of a sudden within days it just
doesn't work and that's a common thing
for manufactured stuff to fail pretty
promptly in its lifetime and then it
gets good and then as time goes on it
just kind of starts to wear out
different things in different ways and
as they wear out they fail more often
and so you know you older cars 20 year
old cars fail more rapidly than one year
old cars but one month old cars fail
more rapidly than one year old cars what
I'm trying to understand is when you
first mentioned you see a lot of
failures on the beginning right when you
set it up I imagine like oh the setup
wasn't correctly there's probably you
know some Mis configuration it's just
the the funkiness of manufacturing
sometimes okay I mean people and you
burn things in the factory burns it in
for a while before they deliver it you
get it into a data center you stack it
up in a rack you burn it in before you
put it into the traffic right and try to
eliminate those initial failures but you
can't end up burning it in so long that
every server you put into into
production doesn't have some initial
failure windows but most of that
beginning of the bathtub curve you test
away in the factory or you test away
before you actually deploy it in the
data center you stack it up you're ready
to deploy it but you've tested it so oh
crap this one's not working so well yeah
that makes sense and with the rise of
cloud computing all of these things of
commissioning and the commissioning
server they're handled by the cloud
provider right for example Amazon Google
correct correct Amazon Google Microsoft
all of those folks would do that that's
just part of the the niceness of the
cloud
IAS approach is is you're buying a bunch
of virtual machines and the cloud
provider themselves will take care of
this aspect of things just like they
worry about the electric bill they worry
about how did I get enough no internet
coming in and out and and it's a great
offloading of a set of services for a
fee to people who can do it more
cost-effectively at volume and with IaaS
you mean infrastructure as a service
right I do
infrastructure as a service this is
we're talking about data centers and
servers let's talk a bit about
maintaining and supporting this data
center particularly prior to DevOps what
did this look like back then well back
in the day you know this is where you're
thinking more of a classic IT shop and
you had hundreds of servers and you had
quite a few people who were managing
them and each of them they would know
and love and I jokingly say come in and
pet in the morning and the software
would be installed by hand people would
worry about the how this particular
server is doing and take care of them
with an awareness of the hardware and
what its needs were and that worked at
small scale tiny scale as we started
putting more and more servers it didn't
become if you have ten times as many
servers it wasn't practical to have ten
times as many you know operators and
support people and so you had to figure
out how this became more automated and
DevOps took us to a world where more of
the stuff was automated more the routine
stuff is automated and so an individual
operator could handle more servers than
before when they were handling every one
with its own personality to do the
DevOps though you had to kind of reduce
the awareness of the personality of each
server and you would say oh I want to do
tens and hundreds of servers with the
same stuff and you are running the same
software and we gonna install it in all
the same software as you get to web
scale and it gets to be hundreds of
thousands of servers you just can't do
that right everything has to be super
automated there
you have to have you know basically no
awareness of the personality of an
individual server as we mentioned
earlier it's got to be kind of like
having a nail in a bag of nails and it's
doing a job and it's contributing but
it's not something you love and care for
and are aware of what its quirks are
yeah I was talking to someone and she
told me that the service even had names
like people would put names to oh yeah
yeah Oh every two oh gosh yes I could
recount lots of names from my past of
you know and you'd be excited to get you
know a fourth one because you had three
in the and you would come up with a name
for the fourth one you got yeah and
that's where we have come from but where
we've come to is just turning that on
its head and you don't know the name of
the server it has a serial number that
you just don't know yeah and she also
said security was a lot of it is the
room secure like the door is locked and
things like that back then
well that's because these things were
not hooked up in sharing a network in
the same way we are today and people
hadn't gotten into you know breaking in
across the network and so security was
definitely limited to the door on the
end the lock on the door yeah um when I
went to college I did drive down to the
University to program there were no pcs
and yes I remember the 120 baud that
means 120 bits per second dial up but it
wasn't practical to program across that
so you'd get up in the morning you take
a shower and you drive down a program at
the computer facility because and then
you didn't worry about security across
the network because there wasn't a darn
network mm-hmm and so this is a
wonderful change it's a it's a great new
and exciting thing but like everything
we see echoes of the past that we came
from you know every city is beat has its
streets laid out for the transportation
of the day and I've been to old
Jerusalem and it was donkeys that were
going between those buildings and it's
still very narrow little windy wet
passages between the buildings and
similarly as we've evolved our computing
in our data centers we carry a heritage
from where we
- but we're inventing new things in a
rapid way and it's really fun and
fascinating so with this we started
talking about ups where there was a lot
of manual work and you had to have a
person assigned particular machines to
take care of then we moved to DevOps
where a lot of things were where
automated you also talked about in your
column this concept of no ops what does
this mean and that's not a common term
that is not a common term but but the
notion is that so much of what had been
done in operation staff just with the
manual operations in the DevOps becomes
you know software managing the servers
and we're constantly seeing this trend
that that the behavior of the servers is
all managed in a way where someone can
detect the software can detect a problem
and can repair the problem and so you
you end up with people only setting the
broad broad broad goals and only dealing
with super rare events that require
attention because almost everything is
automatically handled the thing that to
me you just never want is pagers going
off in the middle of the night on the
weekend you want to go home on Friday
and everyone's doing what they're doing
and then on Monday morning things are
just there and there's some work to do
but nothing was a crisis because it was
all things that went wrong were handled
and we're not all the way there but
we're getting there and and things
continue to change year by year and and
so but to do that to make software able
to handle failures and you have to have
the behavior of the software you're
running the actual application and the
infrastructure that's running has to
have predictable behavior that that the
management software can can handle
imagine I have 50 servers that are
handling a certain class of incoming
requests for example the the you know
something from Amazon comes and it's a
recommendation how many servers are
there to handle the recommendations
stuff that's coming in and if the
traffic goes up in these things are
getting slower because there's too much
work on them automatically roll out more
servers and say you're going to do
commendations and we're gonna send
traffic to you and and have that just
automatically handle it and now the the
responsiveness of that service gets
better because there's more more to
handle the load that stuff should not
require human intervention and we're
we're getting there as an industry we're
getting to the point where that stuff
can be very nicely handled without
people involved so no ops just means ups
that are handled by software where the
human is not involved correct and how
far can we push that and and how much
can we make that be the case and this is
an ongoing area of exploration by the
industry and it's getting better it's
really fun to watch digital ocean is the
easiest cloud platform to deploy manage
and scale applications of any size we're
moving infrastructure friction and
providing predictability so developers
and their teams can deploy faster and
focus on building software that
customers love with thousands of
in-depth tutorials in an active
community we provide the support you
need digitalocean stands out of the
crowd due to its simplicity and high
performance with no billing surprises
try digitalocean for free by getting a
100 dollar infrastructure credit at doco
/se radio I want to talk now more about
developing at scale and using stateless
servers first I want to understand what
operations that scale consists of can
you give a few examples of operations at
scale well just like I said a second to
go about the I want to take this service
and it's going to get traffic and if
it's getting too slow because there's
more traffic than there are servers can
that automatically be increased I see
well that's one example of you know
operations at scale and making that just
work and if you think about it there's a
lot of things that are implementing the
web that that behave that way the front
end for Google things that are doing
certain traffic for Amazon's stuff to
support what we do at Salesforce all of
this stuff the more traffic you have the
more you want to add servers to cope
with the load now being able to
of work handed to any of a bunch of
servers and have each of them able to do
a fine job with that work that's kind of
where we get into the word stateless and
there is no crisp definition for
stateless because a state gets to be
kind of funny but on a whole what it
means is I can use more servers that
didn't know about the last thing you did
it can handle the next thing you want to
do and so they can't really have a an
awareness of what you did before that
they can't go learn from something else
if I have a shopping cart server that's
behind me and I get some traffic and I
can go ask the shopping cart hey what's
in the shopping cart and they get the
answer and do more work for you that's
great and that is considered state less
because the state is often the pool of
shopping cart guys right and so what we
tend to do with load balancing if I have
multiple requests from the same session
the same customer coming in we tend to
send them to the same server and that's
great because even though this server is
stateless it might remember some stuff
from the previous times like oh you know
I went and looked up this customers
preferences or I went and saw the things
they were looking at and I have some of
it left over so if the next request
comes I can do it faster that's still
stateless if that server can go and get
the knowledge from some other part of
the system to cope with the fact that
they're not the one that got the
previous request maybe it's a little
slower because I didn't have it right at
hand and I had to go get it but it still
gives the correct answer so you can have
stateless servers that have some caching
to make the next repeated request from
the same user faster as long as they
give the same correct behavior if you
hit another server that has no cache and
doesn't remember stuff from the past yes
what you're saying is in the shopping
cart application if there's suddenly a
failure you get a new stainless server
and that is gonna ask someone else what
was in the shopping cart and and
therefore be able to pick up where the
user left off correct
for example or the other preferences or
the you're looking for shoes let's show
you some shoes that kind of thing you
know and and there's stuff in that
category where you want to cache that
sometimes and that's the main reason why
stainless servers are designed to fail
right because they they don't need to
well they will fail yeah every server
will fail yeah I mean did every server
will fail on average just ballpark one
out of every five years okay so you can
just do the math right you out of every
two thousand or so servers you're gonna
you know you're gonna lose one every day
right and so you just do the math of
let's take a year and call it four
hundred days because it's easier to do
the math and it's five years so that's
two thousand days so every two thousand
servers I'm gonna come in in the morning
and one of them's broken and that's the
average as you'll see and why don't we
need to do to prepare for our stainless
servers failing well have enough of them
okay and have an ability to bring more
in likely with automation right yeah in
and so you get into this world where if
I have a bunch of extra servers that are
that are good for many different jobs in
the data center you know say there's 500
different jobs in the data center and
each of the servers can do that same any
of those 500 jobs and I've got some
actress over here and I'm losing 20 a
day and I have 150 extras over there and
I go home and tomorrow I come in and and
20 are the actors have been
automatically repositioned to do the
jobs from the ones that failed and then
there's little red lights on the ones
that are broken and you have to like
unplug the ones that are broken and
figure out what you're gonna do to fix
them or buy new ones yes they're just
there it's just automatically how can I
make this stuff work now as I mentioned
the stateless stuff is a little bit
easier to deal with it failing because
you just kind of plug one in you get the
software on it and it doesn't have to
have a lot of knowledge a state full one
well what you want is you watch that
state just like we talked about with
HDFS a few minutes ago you want that
state to be something where oh gee I
have an empty server that's going to
work for this particular storage now
I've got to put data in it how can I get
and it's got a ten terabytes worth of
disk in it great how
can I get 10 terabytes of disk data off
of the other storage servers such that
some of that data has gone down from 3
to 2 replicas and I want to fill it up
with some data that is spread around
that data center because I've only got
one server to fill with say 10 terabytes
it's going to take me a while it'll take
me a day or so to actually get it up to
full by the time I have to copy
everything in across the network unlike
the one that failed when the one that
failed I don't have to put it through
one network connection to refill it that
10 terabytes can be spread out so
managing how the stateful data is is
kept and managing how the state less
computation is kept those are important
tricks for building large-scale data
centers so in the case of the example of
the shopping cart when the server lists
the stateless server is asking for the
shopping cart information they would be
communicating to a stateful service is
that correct correct and you may or may
not want to keep shopping cart data
across interactions but you probably do
because shopping carts are allowed to be
a little bit interact in inaccurate and
and the customer can still be happy but
if you hit a stateless server that
doesn't know you and and and doesn't
know how to find your shopping cart well
that knows how to find it but doesn't
have it already in cache it'll say you
know golly I don't have that and it will
go off to the shopping cart service and
say give me that shopping cart data and
now it'll get it and will do your work
might take it an extra 10 15
milliseconds to get that state from the
shopping cart storage service but it can
get it and you won't notice too bad that
it didn't have it in cash
part of preparing for a failure involves
doing a lot of testing when you're
developing and testing what is the
reason why we use production data
centers because I saw you mention this
in your ACM call them it's hard because
you have a tension that goes on here if
you have dedicated testing data centers
frequently not everywhere but frequently
they end up kind of not having the best
stuff and so now the testing isn't
working against the things that are out
at the cutting edge with production if
you can actually share the production
data center for tests then you end up
usually getting a better representation
of the production environment itself and
a better ability to say wow I've really
tested this thing I know it's going to
work in production because what it got
was the same kind of behavior as
production but the challenge is you want
to make darn sure that your developers
and your testers can't on purpose or on
accident caused a problem with
production okay so you could have you
know a nefarious developer who wants to
go and spy on customer data you can't
let that happen you have to isolate
their access and there have to be you
know ironclad ways to protect the
customers data from all employees and
all other folks you also can have a
situation where the testing could
consume so many resources that you can't
that the production is impacted and so
you have to be able to isolate the tests
from the production resources in order
to do that no it is pretty nice you know
production does go through an ebbing and
the flowing right we're in the middle of
the night there's less traffic at
certain times of year there's less
traffic and so being able to ramp up
your test environment and consume data
center capacity without impacting
production is a very nice thing to be
able to do so you can test in production
like you said as long as you're
isolating the customer data you want to
you want to yes you want to isolate the
customer data and you want to protect
the production performance so that you
don't have too much traffic slowing down
production
that's why prior to testing in
production you can do it in a test
environment right to get an idea of how
the test performs well there's nothing
wrong with having a testing environment
it's it's it's great the the challenges
sometimes are that the test environment
doesn't have the best of the best
because frequently you're when you're
sharing resources and things are scarce
you're hurrying to put things into
into production with the best of the
best now as the big broad data centers
and the VM Technology and sharing of
infrastructure-as-a-service is evolving
this is becoming less of an issue
because you can actually give you know
production and test the best of the best
and give them a lot of good stuff
side-by-side and you know we're seeing
these very large shared cloud
environments are able to isolate their
customers they do they do a phenomenal
job of isolating their customers so that
you one doesn't impact the other another
component for embracing failure before
it embraces you is the use of automated
watchdogs can you explain what these are
well you're watching the the behavior of
a pool of servers and making sure that
the response time is good enough making
sure that things are actually behaving
properly and if I have a hundred servers
that are providing a particular job for
the end you know the customers that are
coming in across the web you want to
watch that the response time for them is
acceptable you want to watch that
they're doing things that are acceptable
they're still alive
so out of those 100 you might want to
actually walk through and talk you know
send a message to each of them saying
hey you alive how you doing and then
that's not perfect but it can be pretty
darn good and making sure that you're
getting a system that you know one of
the 100 that are still doing a good job
if it's not then you want to remove it
from service and you want to replace it
with something that can now run the
software and be up to snuff if the other
one was sick and so you end up with this
how can I test it to make sure the
software is good and the hardware is
good and then pull it out a commission
if it seems suspicious
you you really do want to err on the
side of removing something that seems
inappropriate in its performance or its
behavior and so that you can only have
stuff that seems like it's doing the
right thing and keeping an eye on that
with automated watchdogs is a very
valuable technology does the watchdog
involve humans in some cases well you
don't want it to do it very often or
you're gonna have to buy a lot of humans
yeah well what I mean in the sense of
like you mentioned the watchdog kind of
take something and figure out the
recovery but in some cases do you do you
wanna you know call somebody three
I am usually no not if it's one out of a
hundred for sure and and the the other
thing to realize is it takes some time
to get your head around this you don't
want a sick server you don't want to
coddle it to make it healthy okay you
want to take it offline so the remaining
ones are healthy and then once it's
offline the question is okay can I can I
remove all the data on it can I replace
the software on it and as the physical
server still working okay
and the answer is usually yes but
sometimes no and and so you you just
don't want a sick server if something is
getting full of data we weren't garbage
collecting enough and even rebooting it
isn't good enough to make it better than
you want to take it offline having stuff
that sick only makes the complexity of
the data center higher and having a
higher complexity means you have less
predictability of what you're gonna get
yes that makes sense so it's kind of
ruthless but it is just a server yeah
that's true
and we've been talking about developing
at scale and what this consists of now I
want to shift the conversation to data
at scale because it's an area that
you've worked on a lot and as we are
scaling we see the amount of data
growing how has this changed for example
classical sequel databases have they
changed well yeah I mean they have
they've changed and they haven't but I
think has happened more is that people
don't realize that you can't take sequel
to the cutting edge of size that you can
take other kinds of data the immutable
data by that I mean data that you write
once you read it a bunch of times and
you can eventually throw it away that's
cool but you're not vibrantly changing
it that you can scale it that enormous
paces this just can go like you wouldn't
believe but sequel is only kind of
gradually getting larger in its ability
to handle relational data that you're up
doing you know sequel updates against
and changing because I tend to think of
all of this data in as coming out of
individual stars in the sky and we have
many many scars stars in the galaxy and
many many
galaxies out there each of which is
emitting changes to data but the stuff
in between is all stuff that you wrote
once you're gonna read it many times and
it is what it was and it was what it is
and that's a different attitude towards
things when you look at these ginormous
big data centers and data sets that we
have their data that you write once and
you read it for a bunch of times and
then you throw it away after a while
when you see a big you know company like
Google crawling the web there's a lot of
cool data but you're not updating that
like a sequel database you're writing
things out you've got these immutable
data sets you use them and you do these
incredible things to do searches against
them but it's not a classic updatable
sequel data set not that I don't love
sequel I love sequel I just think it's
one piece of the of the pie of of how do
we build you know and manage data and
when you talk about scale it it's almost
always comes down to things that you
write once and read many big data like
Hadoop and MapReduce is always I've got
a very large data set it's immutable it
never changes I read it I do a
functional operation on it I cross has
that data I produce an output data set
that is immutable also and I have ways
of breaking that up to do parallelism to
get the answer but it is still an
immutable data set in functional
transformation immutable data set out
most of our emerging computational
models follow that same thing so would
you say that one of the main limitations
of sequel is the fact that it's
relational data it's a limitation and a
strength relational is phenomenal
it's brilliant it allowed us to go
amazing places and we still are but at
the same time in order to do the
semantics of the set operations of
relational data you have to make
everything look like it's still well and
everything look like it's here and so to
do that what we have to do is
transactions to make it look still and
then it tends to run on a single
server or a small set of servers that
are close by and so that's a paper I
wrote called the singular success of
sequel and the idea is that it's a
singularity you're collapsing space and
time in order to be able to do the set
operations that's brilliant
but that doesn't run at web scale and so
we haven't as an industry figured out
how to connect those concepts that I use
this here and I use that there that's
still something we're working on
another important thing when working at
scale with data is that data can come
from many different sources what are the
challenges of this this they are coming
from different parts it's a joy data
coming from different sources is just a
phenomenally fascinating area I equate
it to how well do I understand some
person I meet and we all have differing
backgrounds different understandings
differing ways of using words my
granddaughter is 17 she's awesome she is
a teenager I understand about half of
what she says right because she's a
teenager
and and so this ability to understand
data from different sources is very much
the same thing if you're at company a
and you get data from Company B so many
of the expectations and understandings
and environmental concepts are just
wedded to our different worlds right our
different expectations I talk
differently to people on my team at work
than I talked to people in other teams
at work then I talked to someone at a
computing conference talking about
distributed systems then I talked to the
person that who's helping me at a
restaurant and then I talked to my wife
they're all different interactions
having to do with our common expectation
data fits the same pattern what the heck
does that mean how do I understand it
now one of the fascinating things to me
about integration of data is that you've
got a metadata for your data I got a
metadata for my data and what I
interpret yours to be mine some of the
knowledge doesn't move through that
interpretation I call that a lossy
transformation and as I try to get
everything into datasets that I can
understand I lose knowledge based upon
where they're coming from and what's
now what people do frequently is they
say here's the canonical way of
representing an employee or something or
a customer but when you take somebody
else's customer definition and bring it
in great
but that transformation lost some
knowledge now when I go from that
standard canonical one into mine I lost
knowledge and so that is what I call a
double lossy transformation those are
painful but it's what we usually have to
do because of the complexity of the
system yes that's correct
and I wanted to follow up with the shape
of how this data can come in for example
what are some of the different formats
that we might encounter when getting
data from different sources
well data is sometimes formatted to be
understood internally right and when you
have stuff in a relational system it's
it's under it's designed and formatted
to map the DDL when you want to push
something into the outside world and I
call that outside data in a paper I
wrote called data on the inside versus
data on the outside you you want to
describe the metadata for it and usually
you're representing that where it's that
the data is is meant to be read for
common understanding 13 years ago XML
was the the style right now it's JSON is
the style I view them as equivalent JSON
is a little easier to to make the
libraries for but they kind of are the
same thing it's a semi structured data
where you can annotate with your own
metadata and so saying this is what I
meant
at the time I wrote it is super useful
now after that there's Oh Esther what
this means and everybody is brother has
different definitions for what it means
and in my mind the economics of
understanding data at a difference at a
distance it's it's based upon economics
if you have an extremely large retailer
that can tell the manufacturers if you
want to sell in my store because I've
got half of the United States buying out
of my store then you have to have this
representation of the data guess what
the manufacturers are going to figure
out how to fit it into that
representation and that's what I call
the dog wagging the tail
and almost all data integration is
related to which has got the most
economic incentive to map to the other
yes and how do you compensate for the
loss a transformation
you don't okay I mean you can work
harder to make the loss enos less it may
or may not be worth it
in what ways well you can try to have
people in you know team study what did
you mean by this and I'm gonna map it to
that but on a whole you end up having
software that gives it a good good try
and it's good enough it's pretty much
you have tools that do a pretty good job
and then the business need is met and
you don't choose to sit down and try to
understand even more if I have a product
catalog and a bunch of suppliers or
giving me descriptions of products how
do I know that emerald means the same as
Kelly green which means the same as
Forrest green or is it a different thing
or is is short truce a different kind of
green and you end up with all of these
descriptions of these products and
they're kind of a mess and you end up in
a sometimes you apply machine learning
to it where you end up seeing these
patterns and over after a while you say
oh I saw later on that meant the same as
this so I'm gonna probably assume that
means that but this is a there's no
crisp and concrete answer I see to how
you make metadata online I see always
going to be confusing and that's kind of
fun before we finish I want to talk
about the alternatives to sequel which
is called no sequel and I want to talk
about this in the context of scaling but
can you first explain what the
difference between no sequel and sequel
is well sequel is a relational system
that when you bring everything together
and it can handle terabytes tens of
terabytes of data when you bring it
together you can do phenomenal
analysis and phenomenal combinations of
the data in a way that are designed to
let you vibrantly update it and still
have meaning and I continue to believe
that this is an incredible thing that
will move forward but it turns out that
that doesn't work at the web scale to
just say well it's all one big sequel
database because the pressure on making
the changes happen in the pressure
bringing everything together is more
than what works given well frankly speed
of light in distributed systems and
nothing can happen that quickly to make
it that good
so people have kind of built us you know
a bunch of systems which they create a
key value store I don't usually like the
name no sequel because it's less about
no sequel and more about we're storing
stuff in a way which the key and the
value are what we're focusing in on and
when you do that on a whole you don't
end up with many of the rich
characteristics of how do I do queries
and updates against sequel but you get
scale and you get the ability to support
a lot of people and a lot of data doing
a lot of cool things I view both of them
as tools in the toolkit to make a
solution and they're neither right nor
wrong but you have to say what's my
business need and how can I apply
technology to meet what the business
needs and I I mean don't get me wrong I
think scalable key-value is a phenomenal
interesting area and a lot of products
that are really really cool for that but
kind of different one does one thing one
does the other and you give up this to
get that and that's okay
right just I think an area I think is
under discussed in key value stores is
that sometimes you want to have an
answer which does not wait if things are
breaking and things are broken or things
are slow and and we see that you can
actually give a fast answer to a key
value store for a thing like a shopping
cart or something by taking any of the
of a set of recent responses if I'm
gonna do a change I don't necessarily
stall behind a server I'll keep writing
and one of the things I like to say is
do you want it right or do you want it
right now and some business needs want
the faster answer more than they want
the always last answer and that's an
interesting area of research for people
I see what you are saying is there's no
sequel systems or in other terms the key
value systems they give an answer right
now so pretty quickly because they're
fast and they scale but it's not
necessarily the right answer not always
I don't know I'm saying that many no no
no most no most no sequel systems
most key value systems will always do
their best to get you the last answer
that was written to the key but part of
that deal part of what happens there is
that if one of the servers is in fact
exhibiting a sickness and is not well
that may cause the system to go slow for
tens of seconds or a minute and not give
you the answer right away to give you
the perfect answer and they do what
they're designed to do and that for some
uses is the right thing for other uses
you would rather get a recent answer
rather than wait a long time depends
what the business wants and what the
customer wants what's an example for a
business in a use case where the key
value one if I'm reading out of the if
I'm reading out of a product catalog and
I want to see an image of a watch that I
want to buy and the watch is being
updated the description of it is being
updated I'm not that excited about
whether I get an older version or at the
latest version of the watch description
I don't even know and I just want to not
wait for the picture of the watch I'm
gonna be frustrated if if the system
stalls for a minute well it's doing
whatever it does and it turns out even
in many cases for shopping carts that
users leave if it takes a long time to
get an answer to what's in the shopping
cart they don't leave if the last change
to the shopping cart isn't reflected in
the shopping cart and they'll just do
the change again and it kind of settles
out and and so on a rare case you would
prefer to actually give a quick answer
even if it is not necessarily the
perfect answer but it depends upon the
business use and what the customer is
doing and what's best suited to give the
customer what they want yes and for
something more precise it would be
sequel for example like a bank right
well yes for banks but that's not
necessarily sequel it could be you know
a key value store that is doing it but
there are these questions of do I want
to give do I want to wait to get the
perfect answer or do I want to give a
quick answer and it's it's interesting
when you start taking apart what people
do and how things work
and I think this is an area of research
that we're all going to be working on is
how do these distributed systems offer
better behavior for people as time moves
forward
well pod thank you for taking the time
to come on the show it's been great
talking with you about web-scale and
failure and recovery thank you for the
opportunity and it's been great to meet
you and I really appreciate all that you
do for this this is a heck of an
investment of your time and I thank you
for what you're doing for the community
thank you for thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com
you can also email us at team @ SC -
radio net this and all other episodes of
SU radio is licensed under Creative
Commons license 2.5 thanks for listening